Guide to Culinary Ephemera: Flour Products, Leavening Agents, and Baked Goods ams.0058
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
- Flour Products
  - Box 15
    Standard Milling Co.
    - Washburn-Crosby Co.'s new Gold Medal cook book. 71 p., 1904 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes Washburn-Crosby's Gold Medal Flour. Includes recipes for cleaning materials and medicines; menus; tables of measures, proportions, and cooking times; advertisements for Gold Medal Flour with product packaging and factory illustrations; coupons for cook book; and index. Newspaper clipping of poem by Ella Wheeler Wilcox, 1914, laid in. Some recipes include wine, beer, or liquor as an ingredient. Sample recipes: venison pasty, royal croquettes, and squash muffins.
    - The Pillsbury cook book. 126 p., 1913 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      Item [2] promotes Pillsbury's Best Flour. Compiled by Nellie Duling Gans, who won Medal of Honor for perfect bread at St. Louis World's Fair. Includes household hints; tables of weights and measures, proportions, and cooking times; tables of contents of recipes and illustrations (sketches of cultivation and manufacture of flour, factory, and Minneapolis); information on yeast; coupons for cook book and pass for visiting the Pillsbury A Mill; and index. Some recipes include wine, beer, or liquor as an ingredient. Sample recipes: Vienna rolls, roast wild duck, and wine whey.
    - The Pillsbury cook book. 126 p., 1923 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      Item [3] promotes Pillsbury's Best Flour. Similar to item [2] except for slightly modified cover title, cover illustrations, and copyright date. 2 copies.
    - Washburn-Crosby's Gold Medal cook book. 74 p., 1917 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Washburn-Crosby's Gold Medal Flour. Revised version of item [1] including some new recipes, improved recipe layout, and poem on breadmaking. Sample recipes: shad roe croquettes, Lyonnaise potatoes, and Lancashire tea cakes. 2 copies.
    - Washburn Crosby's Gold Medal cook book. 74 p., 1917 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      Item [5] promotes Washburn Crosby's Gold Medal Flour. Similar to item [4] except that coupons for purchasing item are replaced by message from Betty Crocker noting that new Gold Medal home service (boxed card index of recipes with updates) will replace this final edition of cook book.
    - Pillsbury's cook book. 96 p., 1921 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      Item [6] promotes Pillsbury's Best Flour. Completely revised version of items [2] and [3]. Includes company history; tables of cooking times, weights, and measures; Pillsbury mills, period dress, serving suggestion, and product packaging illustrations; information on preserving fruit and eggs from U.S. Dept. of Agriculture bulletins, and on yeast; blank pages for adding recipes; and index. Sample recipes: broiled quail, maple frango, and crullers.
    - Pillsbury's cook book. 78 p., 1923 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes Pillsbury's Best Flour. Modified version of item [6]. Sections on preserving fruit, eggs, and yeast, blank pages for additional recipes, and several full page advertisements for Best Flour are missing. Recipes appear unchanged.
    - Simple, easy, fair: enter Pillsbury's $10,000.00 contest: [broadside]., 1935 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes Pillsbury's Best Flour. Includes announcement of $10,000 contest ($3,000 first prize) for statement with greatest advertising value, containing at most 20 words, all taken from lengthier statement promoting Pillsbury's Best Flour by Mary Ellis Ames, director of Pillsbury's cooking service; contest rules; and names of judges. No recipes.
    - [Henkel's extra fancy flours: letter]., circa 1930s (Box 15, Folder 9)
      Item [9] promotes Henkel's flours. Form letter in response to order for Henkel recipe book for use with Henkel's Velvet Cake and Pastry Flour. Letter also promotes Henkel's Self-Rising Pancake Flour with "recipes printed on the box." Includes illustrations of Henkel mill, office, and garage. No recipes.
    - Pillsbury's diamond anniversary recipes. 1 v. (unpaged), 1944 (Box 15, Folder 10)
      Item [10] promotes Pillsbury's flours on Pillsbury's 75th anniversary. Includes romantic illustrated account by Ann Pillsbury, director of Pillsbury's Home Service Dept., of "grandmother" looking after her family in her younger pioneering days, contrasted with modern life and conveniences such as Pillsbury's flour; and illustrations of the stages of making flour from ancient to modern times, serving suggestions, and product packaging. Sample recipes: chicken dinner pie, jelly jumbles, and lucky seven rolls. Marked: 55-2.
    - The baker's formula booklet: breads, variety breads, sweet goods. 60 p., circa 1960s (Box 15, Folder 11)
      Item [11] promotes Pillsbury flours. Looseleaf, typewritten, and reproduced on 3-hole-punch paper, with glossy cover with product packaging illustration. Index. Sample recipes: salty rye bread, coffee cake, and fruit muffins.
    - Heckers & Ceresota, the twin flours. 1 v. (unpaged)., circa 1980s (Box 15, Folder 12)
      Item [12] promotes Heckers and Ceresota flours. Includes information on unbleached, natural white flour, kneading, freezing bread, and shaping loaves; whimsical cover illustration of old-fashioned kitchen with two bonneted cooks preparing bread; and product packaging and serving suggestion illustrations. Sample recipes: anadama bread, creamy peach pie, and choca-cola cake.
    - [King Arthur flour: folder containing 5 loose sheets]., circa 1990s (Box 15, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes King Arthur Flour. Loose sheets inside folder include 4-page history of company, "America's oldest flour company;" details for ordering the King Arthur baker's catalogue with list of lifetime baking products; promotion of the King Arthur Flour 200th anniversary cookbook by Brinna Sands with picture, information on its development and how to order, and testimonials; "a personal perspective" on Sands, Taylor & Wood Co. from Frank and Brinna Sands; and information on King Arthur Flour. No recipes.
    - 50 scrumptious ways to dessert your family. 23 p., 1971 (Box 15, Folder 14)
      Item [14] promotes Betty Crocker dessert mixes. Includes serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations, advertisement for cake decorations and balloons from Pioneer Products, and index. Sample recipes: grasshopper pie, easy petits fours, and Williamsburg trifle.
    - The baker's catalogue. 55, [1] p., circa 1960s (Box 15, Folder 15)
      Item [15], a "catalogue of fine tools, ingredients, equipment, and recipes for the home baker" edited by P. J. Hamel, promotes King Arthur Flour. Includes illustrations of product packaging for variety of products, kitchen equipment, Polish pottery, and serving suggestions; order form; list of dates and locations for national bread making classes in 2002; map and directions for store in Connecticut; and index. Sample recipes: coffee toffee brownies, pineapple paradise cake, and soft garlic knots.
    - A guide to Pillsbury cookbooks and premiums 1869-1969 / [by Frank Daniels]. 28 (html) p., 2001 (Box 15, Folder 16)
      Item [16], apparently published only online (at www.friktech.com/pills/pills1.htm), promotes Pillsbury cookbooks. Includes history of Pillsbury; chronological listing of Pillsbury cookbooks, pamphlets, advertising items, etc. with (some of) title, paging, dimensions, "scarcity index," and price; and information on collectibility of listed items. No recipes.
  - Box 20.
    American Dairy Asociation.
    - Pillsbury's combined recipe book and premium list. 36 p., 1902-1903 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      Item [1] has an advertisement laid in; a catalog of items with value in proofs of purchase; illustrations include: Game of Silverlocks and the three bears, pin the tail on the donkey, and table tennis.
    - A kernel's story. 16 p., 1905 (Box 20, Folder 2)
      Item [2] has a cookbook order form laid in; the story of raising wheat and conversion into flour for sale in the 1900's; equipment illustrated.
    - 100 prize-winning recipes: 2nd Grand National. 100 p., 1951 (Box 20, Folder 3)
      Item [3] is winning recipes from 2nd baking contest; recipes are attributed with formal names.
    - 100 prize winning recipes: 3rd Grand National. 96 p., 1953 (Box 20, Folder 4)
      Item [4] is winning recipes from 3rd baking contest; recipes are attributed (some with illustrations of winner) using formal names.
    - The most-wanted cooky recipes in all America: [folded brochure], 1952 (Box 20, Folder 5)
      Item [5] includes attributed recipes from 1st, 2nd, and 3rd contest; uses formal names; includes premimum coupon.
    - 100 prize winning recipes: 4th Grand National. 96 p., 1952 (Box 20, Folder 6)
      Item [6] is winning recipes from 4th baking contest; recipes are attributed (some with illustration of winner) using formal names.
    - Pillsbury's 5th 100 Grand National recipes. 96 p., 1954 (Box 20, Folder 7)
      Item [7] is winning recipes from 5th baking contest; recipes are attributed (some with illustrations of winner) using formal names.
    - Pillsbury's 7th Grand National cookbook. 98 p., 1956 (Box 20, Folder 8)
      Item [8] is winning recipes from 7th baking contest; recipes are attributed (illustrations include current and past winners) using formal names.
    - 100 Grand National recipes: [8th] 96 p., circa 1957 (Box 20, Folder 9)
      Item [9] is winning recipes from 8th baking contest; recipes are attributed with some illustrations using formal and informal names.
    - 11 of America's most treasured cake recipes. 16 p., circa 1951 (Box 20, Folder 10)
      Item [10] includes attributed recipes from 1st, 2nd, and 3rd contests, some are illustrated with winner.
    - Party best butter cookies. 28 p., 1900s (Box 20, Folder 11)
      Item [11] has many recipes developed by the American Dairy Association to promote use of butter, some contest winning recipes.
    - Jewel-box butter cookies. 28 p., 1900s (Box 20, Folder 12)
      Item [12] recipes contain ingredients from multiple sponsors and prior contest winning recipes.
    - Newest bake-off recipes. 16 p., circa 1964 (Box 20, Folder 13)
      Item [13] was a magazine insert; contains recipes and illustrated advertisements for General Electric ranges circa 1964.
    - Announcing the new Pillsbury family cookbook: [coupon], circa 1940s (Box 20, Folder 14)
      Item [14] is a discount coupon for the New Pillsbury family cookbook.
    - "Balanced" recipes: [folded brochure], circa 1940s (Box 20, Folder 15)
      Item [15] is folder no. 3 of a series of flour inserts and includes recipes and advertisements for radio show featuring Mary Ellis Ames.
    - "Do-it-together" butter cookies. 32 p., circa 1965 (Box 20, Folder 16)
      Item [16] features Pillsbury Instant Blending Flour recipes; has a section on projects using flour based modeling clay.
    - Calorie slim recipes. 64 p., circa 1960s (Box 20, Folder 17)
      Item [17] has Sweet*10 sweetener recipes; menus for various total calorie diets.
    - Mary Ellis Ames brings you another group of... Pillsbury's famous "balanced" recipes: [folded brochure], circa 1940s (Box 20, Folder 18)
      Item [18] is folder no. 4 of series with item [15]; has coupon for Balanced recipe cookbook.
    - Every "balanced" recipe has an official OK: [folded brochure], circa 1940s (Box 20, Folder 19)
      Item [19] is folder no. 7 of a series with item [15].
    - These new "balanced" recipes have been developed and proved by Pillsbury's cooking service: [folded brochure], circa 1940s (Box 20, Folder 20)
      Item [20] is an unnumbered flour insert with recipes.
    - Create cookie magic: [folded brochure], 1984 (Box 20, Folder 21)
      Item [21] flour insert with recipe for basic cookie mix and variations.
    - Desserts: [folded brochure], 1942 (Box 20, Folder 22)
      Item [22] is folder no. 19, form PB M-1778-A; includes recipes and Thrift Star coupons.
    - 100 delicious foods from 4 basic recipes. 30 p., 1927 (Box 20, Folder 23)
      Item [23] has recipes for: White bread, bisquits, loaf cake, and cookies with variations; later edition of item [26].
    - Good bread and how to make it. 16 p., 1929 (Box 20, Folder 24)
      Item [24] has Waldo Lincoln presentation sticker pasted in; instructions for drying flour before using for better measurement.
    - A book for a cook. 128 p., 1905 (Box 20, Folder 25)
      Item [25] was compiled by Mrs. Nellie Duling Gans after winning the grand prize for bread at the 1904 World's Fair at St. Louis, Mo.; illustrated with stages of growing and processing wheat into flour.
    - 100 delicious foods from 4 basic recipes. 22 p., 1927 (Box 20, Folder 26)
      Item [26] is an earlier edition of item [23].
    - Fun-filled butter cookie cookbook. 48 p., 1956 (Box 20, Folder 27)
      Item [27] has attributed recipes from first seven baking contests.
    - Pillsbury's cook book. 48 p., 1930 (Box 20, Folder 28)
      Item [28] was supervised by the Pillsbury Laboratory; includes recipes for foods not using flour as well as baked goods.
    - Bread flour cookbook. 16 p., 1979 (Box 20, Folder 29)
      Item [29] was included with flour purchase; dough making process illustrated.
    - Pillsbury's best butter cookie cookbook. 52 p., circa 1957 (Box 20, Folder 30)
      Item [30] is vol. 2; includes recipes from first 8 contests plus European recipes modified for U.S.
    - Best loved foods of Christmas. 65 p., circa 1960 (Box 20, Folder 31)
      Item [31] includes recipes from first 10 contests plus European recipes modified.
    - Pillsbury's best flour: four easy receipts. 11 p., circa 1920s (Box 20, Folder 32)
      Item [32] has theory of breadmaking (from 1920?).
    - 100 prize-winning recipes: [1st] 96 p., 1950 (Box 20, Folder 33)
      Item [33] recipes from 1st baking contest; attributed with formal names; first edition.
  - Box 21.
    - 100 Prize-winning Grand National recipes: from Pillsbury's 6th Grand National. 96 p., 1955 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      Item [1] has attributed recipes from the 6th baking contest; some winners' portraits are included, with comments. Uses formal names. Cost 25 cents.
    - Pillsbury's Best 10th Grand National bake-off cookbook. 106 p., circa 1959 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      Item [2] is similar to [1] with added recipes from sponsors. Bisquick coupons laid in.
    - Pillsbury's Best 11th Grand National bake-off cookbook. 104 p., circa 1960 (Box 21, Folder 3)
      Item [3] is similar to [1]; has inscription: Evelyn Taylor.
    - Pillsbury's Best 12th Grand National bake-off cookbook. 95 p., circa 1961 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      Item [4] is similar to [1]; entry blank and rules are missing.
    - Pillsbury's 13th Grand National bake-off cookbook. 94 p., circa 1962 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      Item [5] is similar to [1]; errata sheet laid in. Cost 35 cents.
    - Pillsbury's 14th Grand National bake-off cookbook. 96 p., circa 1963 (Box 21, Folder 6)
      Item [6] is similar to [1]; winners' portraits in middle pages.
    - 100 new bake-off recipes: from Pillsbury's 15th Grand National. 92 p., 1964 (Box 21, Folder 7)
      Item [7] only has major winners' portraits; rules don't allow intoxicating beverages as ingredients.
    - 100 new bake-off recipes: from Pillsbury's 16th Grand National. 95 p., 1965 (Box 21, Folder 8)
      Item [8] many recipes are adapted by Ann Pillsbury. Cost 50 cents.
    - The Pillsbury busy lady bake-off recipes: from the 17th annual bake-off. 95 p., 1966 (Box 21, Folder 9)
      Item [9] recipes are "shortcutted and up-to-dated by Pillsbury". No winner portraits are included.
    - Bake-off cook book: from the 18th annual bake-off. 96 p., 1967 (Box 21, Folder 10)
      Item [10] is similar to [9]. Cost 79 cents.
    - Bake-off cook book: from the 19th annual bake off. 94 p., 1968 (Box 21, Folder 11)
      Item [11] is similar to [9]. Cost 98 cents.
    - 100 Bake-off recipes: from the 20th annual bake off. 94 p., 1969 (Box 21, Folder 12)
      Item [12] is similar to item [9].
    - Bake it easy bake-off cook book: 100 winning recipes from Bake-Off 24. 96 p., circa 1973 (Box 21, Folder 13)
      Item [13] has list of all previous grand prize winners. Cost 89 cents.
    - America's Bake-off cookbook: 100 winning recipes from Bake-Off 29. 95 p., circa 1978 (Box 21, Folder 14)
      Item [14] adds nutritional information; adds informal names. Cost $1.59; has bar code on cover.
  - Box 30.
    Mills, Mary.
    Mack, Peggy.
    Steinbarger, Mabel.
    Henkel, F. Y.
    Southwestern Milling Company.
    Eagle Roller Mill Company.
    Acme-Evans Company.
    Everett, Aughenbaugh & Co.
    Elam Mills.
    Pure Gluten Food Company.
    Geo. V. Hecker & Co.
    Boston Cooking School (Boston, Mass.)
    Heckler & Brother.
    Gwinn Milling Co.
    Commercial Milling Company.
    International Milling Company.
    Toledo Grain & Milling Co.
    Northwestern Consolidated Milling Co.
    - Aristos recipes: kitchen wisdom. 32 p. (2 copies), 1911 (Box 30, Folder 1)
      Item [1] has hints for using Aristos flour in cakes and pies.
    - Daniel Webster Flour cook book. 120 p., 1907 (Box 30, Folder 2)
      Item [2] includes illustration of the factory. The theory of bread baking from the Boston Cooking School cook book is on p.8.
    - Valuable recipes: Optima the best flour. [folded brochure], circa 1910s (Box 30, Folder 3)
      Item [3] may have been an insert in the flour package.
    - Recipes you'll like: [folded brochure], 1928 (Box 30, Folder 4)
      Item [4] has color illustrations of flour packaging and a woman and child in period dress.
    - The Fisher's Blend baking book. 164 p., 1941 (Box 30, Folder 5)
      Item [5] has chapters introduced with hints for successful preparation. Recipes attributed to Mary Mills.
    - Guaranteed always all right: E-A-CO. 24 p., circa 1930s (Box 30, Folder 6)
      Item [6] contains illustrations of the old and new factories; illustrated equipment used to manufacture flour; and discussion of flour manufacturing process.
    - 101 Ways to a man's heart. 24 p., circa 1950s (Box 30, Folder 7)
      Item [7] has non-attributed winning recipes from the E-Z Bake contest.
    - Elam's recipes: for old fashioned whole grain cereals and stone ground flours: [folded brochure], circa 1960s (Box 30, Folder 8)
      Item [8] describes 44 years of milling only whole grain products.
    - Recipes from the Martha Gooch kitchens. 20 p., circa 1958 (Box 30, Folder 9)
      Item [9] has illustrations of product offerings from Gooch's Best.
    - Eventually, Washburn Crosby's Gold Medal flour, why not now?: [booklet for notes] 32 p., 1916 (Box 30, Folder 10)
      Item [10] has blank lined pages with calendar. Coupons have illustration of Washburn-Crosby Co. factory.
    - The Gold Medal sandwich book. 38 p., circa 1920s (Box 30, Folder 11)
      Item [11] has history of the sandwich and is dedicated to the Earl of Sandwich.
    - Recipes for cooking Gum Gluten foods. 24 p., circa 1901 (Box 30, Folder 12)
      Item [12] describes a diet free from starch, with menus.
    - Gold Medal Flour: [trade card], circa 1980s (Box 30, Folder 13)
      Item [13] is an invitation to the Wondra Challenge at the IACP Information fair.
    - Heckers' Croton Flour Mills. 36 p., 1869 (Box 30, Folder 14)
      Item [14] has illustrations of the flour mill; discussion of farina, hominy, and corn grits. Wine and alchohol are used as ingredients.
    - Better baking: with Gwinn's Jefferson crushed wheat flour. 36 p., circa 1920s (Box 30, Folder 15)
      Item [15] contains illustrated history of Gwinn Milling Company and the new flour mill.
    - Heckers' household hints: series 2. 36 p., circa 1920s (Box 30, Folder 16)
      Item [16] the cover illustrated a period kitchen; includes hints and recipes.
    - Some good things to bake. 44 p., circa 1920s (Box 30, Folder 17)
      Item [17] has illustrations of test kitchen and Mabel Steinbarger.
    - Good things to eat. 64 p., 1934 (Box 30, Folder 18)
      Item [18] is part of a series for Henkel's Extra Fancy Flours. Cover has period illustration of women at a card table. Wine is included as an ingredient.
    - Good things to eat. 64 p. (2 copies), 1939 (Box 30, Folder 19)
      Item [19] is similar to item [18]. The two copies have different back cover illustrations.
    - For cake that's good tomorrow, too: [folded brochure], circa 1940s (Box 30, Folder 20)
      Item [20] the letter is illustrated with the mill and office. The letter is from F. Y. Henkel and is laid in.
    - Good things to eat: with Henkel's flour. 45 p., 1934 (Box 30, Folder 21)
      Item [21] has the period theory of cake baking on p. 17.
    - Good things to eat: made with Velvet Cake and Pastry Flour. 22 p. (2 copies), 1954 (Box 30, Folder 22)
      Item [22] is a continuation of the series, mostly cake recipes.
    - A short course with King Arthur Flour in baking with yeast. 28 p., 1985 (Box 30, Folder 23)
      Item [23] has discussion of ingredient effect on recipes.
    - King Arthur Flour: America's oldest flour company: [folded brochure], circa 1990s (Box 30, Folder 24)
      Item [24] has illustrated history of Sands, Taylor, and Wood Co.
    - New easy to make recipes using King Arthur Flour: [folded brochure], circa 1940s (Box 30, Folder 25)
      Item [25] is a typical package insert for flour.
    - The King Arthur Flour baker's catalogue. 32 p., 1991 (Box 30, Folder 26)
      Item [26] is an illustrated catalog of home baking equipment, with prices.
    - King Arthur Flour's baking class recipes. 32 p., circa 1991 (Box 30, Folder 27)
      Item [27] has a section on bread baking problem solving.
    - Oh, please mamma! 24 p.28, circa 1920s (Box 30, Folder 28)
      Item [28] cover is period art, lots of illustrations of flour packaging.
    - White Lily cake recipes. 17 p., circa 1980s (Box 30, Folder circa 1980s)
      Item [29] has recipes for white lily cake.
    - Camp's Pansy Flour: 44 years Toledo's favorite: [folded brochure], circa 1940s (Box 30, Folder 30)
      Item [30] has advertisement for a radio show on WSPD with Peggy Mack.
    - Ceresota cook book. 44 p., circa 1910s (Box 30, Folder 31)
      Item [31] has color illustrations of prepared dishes, recipe laid in.
    - Good things to eat: made with Henkel's flour. 43 p., circa 1930s (Box 30, Folder 32)
      Item [32] has a recipe for gold and silver cake.
  - Box 31.
    Martin, Rita.
    Parker, Marion Jane.
    Hunter, Francis Tipton.
    Downing, Helen Harrington.
    Robin Hood Flour Mills.
    Peavey Company Flour Mills.
    Reliable Flour Co.
    Montana Flour Mills Co.
    Midland Flour Milling Co.
    International Milling Co.
    International Multifoods Corporation.
    Roman Meal Company.
    - Town Crier baking guide. 24 p., circa 1940s (Box 31, Folder 1)
      Item [1] has illustrations of the factory and a period kitchen.
    - "From the kernel to the loaf": a story on flour. 24 p., 1916 (Box 31, Folder 2)
      Item [2] has illustrations of the factory, period dress, farming with horse and steam power, and a map of Montana hard wheat growing areas. Stamped Welch & French, Agts. New York.
    - The children's party book / Marion Jane Parker. 40 p., 1924 (Box 31, Folder 3)
      Item [3] includes period illustrations of children's dress and parties. Illustrated by Frances Tipton Hunter; recipes by Helen Harrington Downing.
    - Occident recipes: cookies: [folded brochure], circa 1929 (Box 31, Folder 4)
      Item [4] is part of an Occident flour series; doughnuts recipe calls for frying in lard.
    - Occident recipes: desserts: [folded brochure], circa 1929 (Box 31, Folder 5)
      Item [5] is similar to [4]; has recipe for suet pudding.
    - Occident recipes: yeast breads: [folded brochure], circa 1929 (Box 31, Folder 6)
      Item [6] is similar to [4]; has recipe for German kuchen.